hello everyone my name is greg and i
deaf stuff welcome everyone to episode 2
of the tactics game in unity
today we want to introduce clicking
things on the map and placing a map
let's rescale our terrain a little
select the main camera and let's create
another new component called grid
control
inside immediately create the serialized
target grid variable
this way we can reference the grid we
will be interacting from the scene
so what we're going to do is to click on
the screen with a mouse
and send the array towards the terrain
object
when i intersect with the terrain we
will get the position of the point of
intersection
and using this position we will
determine the position on the grid
based on the size of each node
so let's make a serialized field for
terrain layer mask
so when you will be shooting the ray you
can ignore every other collider except
the terrain
okay now in the update if you press left
mouse button we want to shoot the array
from the screen towards the terrain
from the point of the mouse pointer
to do this create a new ray which will
be
shot from the main camera using screen
point to ray
then call physics raycast
which will cast the array we have
created
we need to store the raycast heat
information into the variable
then we want to use layer mask
and recast
wants to have a length of the ray in
that case
just tell it to have a float
maxwell or length
if we put all of this into the if
statement that means everything inside
those brackets will be executed only if
you hit something
in our case only if you hit terrain
so inside those brackets we want to pass
our world position from the heat
to the target grid and get the converted
wall position into the grid position
so inside we want to calculate the
position on the grid calculate the
position relative to the grid to do this
offset the world position by the
transform position
now calculate position on grid by
dividing the world position by the cell
size
disclaimer
i'm aware that this
offsetting of the grid is not efficient
and will give a performance hit we will
optimize the grid in the next episode
and i will give you explanation when you
want to keep all of those calculation in
instead of removing them for
optimization
post the position on the grid into debug
let's set up fields set the terrain and
set the layer
move the camera for better view
launch the game and let's see
good as you can see it works it might
look a little weird because the camera
makes it a little distorted
this episode is brought to you by
generous support of people on patreon
and members on youtube if you want to
join them link to my patreon in the
description and join button available
right now on youtube
now let's talk about placing object on
our grid you see one of the important
things you want to do is to ensure the
ability to prototype and test your game
as fast as possible
that includes the ability to just pick a
character and plop him into the scene
and he will work immediately
so what we're going to create now is
grid object
an
object which is present on the grid
before let's clean our scene a little by
attaching obstacles to the terrain and
attaching terrain to the grid
now let's create a capsule to represent
the character on the scene
who will be our grid object
actually let's place the
capsule into an empty object container
then rename the container into character
create another new component called
character to the character object
open the character script and add a new
serialized variable called name
actually make it public
good
now create another new script grid
object
open newly created script
created script will be responsible for
character stats and attributes meanwhile
grid object will be responsible for
placing our character onto the grid and
interacting with this grid
so think about this like this character
is your rpg system it's it's hp's its
names it's what kind of way upon this
character is holding
meanwhile
uh
the grid object is half this character
will move around you know past finding
placing the character in the grid
interacting with the script that's the
point
inside this script onstart create and
call a new script called init
in this method get the position on grid
for this object
by passing the position of the object
then using this position place the
object on the grid
create a new method in the grid to place
the object
path position and the object itself
using this keyboard
inside the place object simply place the
object into a node for this we will have
to create a new public variable in the
node
assign grid to the field
where we test the field make a debug
message
which will post the name of the object
in the grid to do this create a new
method called getplaceobject and pass
the grid position
return the grid object out of the grid
using this grid position
then check if the grid object which we
returned out of the grid is known
then post a message that this position
is empty
otherwise post the name of the character
doing something like this is not very
efficient so we will remove this soon it
just for testing purposes
if we launch the game right now it will
draw an error
this is because our node are not
initialized yet
add initialization of nodes in the
create grid
and now you have witnessed what is
called an out of order error you see we
have initialized the nodes but our
object still draws the same error this
is happening because the object is being
placed into the grid at the start
meanwhile
the grid is being generated at the start
too
that means there is a chance that cell
object will be placed before the grid is
initialized
to avoid this from happening let's
initialize a grid on the awake
which always
always fires up before the start
this will fix the error
now let's try to place the object inside
the grid this will draw an index out of
range exception
this exception or error if you want is
caused by trying to access the array
outside its boundaries
as you can see our character stands way
outside the boundaries of the grid
what we need to do is inside the place
object method call a boundaries check
so create a new method called check
boundary inside we want to do a check
for boundaries so check if the position
on grid passed as the parameter is
inside the length and width of the grid
if it is inside
return true otherwise return false
use check boundaries to limit the
placement of the object if check
boundaries return true
only then place an object
good
let's post an message if you are trying
to place an object in outside the
boundaries
now if you keep clicking around outside
the terrain everything is okay because
we are not registering a heat but inside
the terrain the unity will draw an error
similar to the one we had with placed
object
well it can be fixed exactly the same
way
in the get placed object call check
boundary and in case we are inside the
boundaries return object otherwise
return null
so every time you interact with the grid
you want to check boundaries in case
you're trying to interact with the grid
outside its boundaries
good this is it for this episode if you
have any questions or any ideas about
code please leave your comment below if
you are interested in seeing what will
come out of this please subscribe if you
want to support further you can find my
patreon in the description special thank
you too and ruby long for his generous
support with best regards see you in the
next episode
you